One time I was on my deathbed, the
doctor told me that I was going to die
tomorrow.
This is Brian [music] Atwell. He grinded
to a senior staff engineer at Uber in
under 4 years, and now he's the CTO at
Travis Kalanick's current company, and
he came with some insane war stories.
One time at Uber, I was walking home and
I collapsed on the side of the street.
My chest was aching and I couldn't move
any part of my body. You grinded an
obscene amount to get to where you are
today. If you want to be senior staff at
one of the world's best tech companies
by the time you're 25, this is the only
way to do it. He also dropped brutally
honest takes about how big tech actually
works. I held off saying this, but
Google had this policy where they want
to keep as many smart people on staff as
possible, and they didn't want their
competitors to have them. He had a
run-in with Steve Jobs that didn't go
how he hoped.
>> Like I really made Steve Jobs think I
was an idiot. And he also opened up
about what it's like working directly
with Travis Kalanick. He says, "Guys,
the core problem here is that this is
lazy. You're over-indexing on scope.
It's uninsightful. You could do so much
better. It's worth your time to do
better." Why is this company so strict
on privacy? [music]
We don't usually talk about it, but I
talked to Travis about it and he said,
"I could give you a bit more than we've
given anybody before." This was just the
surface. Here's the full episode.
Your career grew really quickly to
senior staff at Uber. I mean, you got
there in less than 4 years after
graduating college. And I kind of want
to go over the story of that. So, what
would you say are some of the top things
and the highlights that led to your
growth?
If I think about it, probably the things
that
uh really helped a lot is that fairly
shortly after graduation, I went to
Uber. And early Uber was just a
fantastic engineering firm, right?
There's good people to learn from.
They're very meritocratic and they're
growing, so there's lots of problems,
right? They're They were uh
You don't have to be growing to have
problems, but it is one way to have a
lot of good problems to solve.
And um the other thing is that I just
naturally I care a lot about my team.
You can't You can't succeed
if you're selfish in the long run.
Doesn't work out. Team sport.
All right. So, so those kind of things
were just natural and I got for free.
But, the things that um I intentionally
did is that I cultivated this tolerance
of extreme pain.
Um and pain tolerance early in your your
career, a lot of this is just work
ethic. And if you plot
um engineers' career growth against
how much work they do, it's a it's like
a linear relationship.
Uh it's at least linear. It's actually
superlinear for a lot of it.
Because of the compounding effect of how
much you work.
Um and this is especially true because
managers will only give the really
valuable work, uh the really strategic,
the technical, the kind of things that
helps you with your career, once you've
already proven you're good at it. And
sometimes you just got to go and you got
to make time to learn that yourself. So,
I do think that working, pushing really
hard early on does have outsized
returns. I actually don't totally buy
that that means you should stop after,
cuz there's always like more levels you
can grow, right? There's also levels
that haven't been invented yet. So, you
could do that. Um but uh certainly this
is something that I thought about early
on. Like when I joined Uber, I was I was
very aware that um I had more time than
I'd ever have in my future, and that if
I was going to invest in growing this,
it'd be the easiest time to do it. It
sounds like you grinded an obscene
amount to get to where you are today or
to kind of grow as much as you did. And
I'm curious, like looking back, was it
worth it?
You know, one time I was on my deathbed
and I was told the doctor told me that I
was going to die
tomorrow.
And I was sitting on uh I was sitting
there and thinking like, "Damn, I'm
going to die. That sucks. I haven't
accomplished anything yet. There's like
so much stuff professionally I want to
do."
Right? So, that expression of like,
"You're never going to think about
wanting to spend more time in the office
on your deathbed" is not true.
Right? Like I went back when they found
out they messed up my medication. I
worked harder than ever. And yeah, I
totally overdid it sometimes, but the
the times that that I pushed really
hard, they were fun. They were like
being in a soccer game where you're tied
until the last minute and then you score
or somebody else scores, your team wins,
and it was painful, but you look back on
the your head and you're like, "That was
great." So, when you were on your
deathbed, you you weren't saying, "Oh, I
have regrets that, you know, I I didn't
travel more, do that." Your your regret
was, "I wish I worked harder." Yeah, it
actually was, yeah.
Yeah, I was like, "Shit, I'm going to
die." Aw, I was really looking forward
to building some cool stuff. I was
really looking forward to that. And uh
then I got out and I was on an
internship and I went back to work the
next week and I just worked harder.
So, everyone has a breaking point.
Obviously, you can't work, you know, 168
hours a week. Where is that breaking
point for you and like how do you know
when you're working too much?
Uh I think the best way to know, I have
an hours number in my head, but that's
less useful. The way that I know is that
if I start to get a little grumpy. Like
if I, let's say that I work
uh a few weeks without taking any day
off, I'll start to get a little bit
grumpy. I'll be less patient with
people. And I'm in management, so I
really have to be patient.
Um so, that's that when that starts to
happen, usually my partner will tell me
and I'm like, "Oh, yeah, of course. I
haven't taken a day off in weeks."
>> [laughter]
>> Right? Um this is me catching it earlier
than when I was younger. Right? Like one
time at Uber, um
I was walking home and I collapsed on
the side of the street. Uh my chest was
aching and I couldn't move any part of
my body for 15 minutes. I just watched
people walk by me. Right? Like in that
moment, I knew I should have cut back by
5%.
>> [laughter]
>> Right? I was like, "I knew it." But,
ideally I would have known that a little
sooner. Did you go to the doctor after
that or like what was that? Yeah, I did
and there was nothing where they were
like, "I don't know, you're just you're
too anxious. You're working too much."
If you if you don't take time off
and just like every moment of your
waking day is is trying to do really
high-quality work, um your anxiety
levels go up over time. It's the same
reason that that like professional
athletes are really intense. They're
training all the time, but they aren't
conscious about taking time off to let
themselves, their body, their mind
regenerate. Are there any concrete
stories you can tell me that kind of
illustrate like how you grew as an
engineer?
There's this guy called Yi Wang.
Uh we both joined the same team at Uber.
He'd been there for a few years before
we joined. The reason for this team was
to uh
fix some of the maintainability issues
that were happening in mobile as the
company hyper-scaled. So, we're the most
junior guys. Every day we overhear some
kind of big debate on the team.
Like we'd hear, "Hey, should we use
RxJava streams emitted from this
library?
Um would that make a lot of these issues
go away or should we use some other more
conventional type of multi-thread work
distribution system? Should we do
something else?"
And I overhear people uh use their
experience to prune out the worst
options. Right? That's like fairly easy.
And then picking the best option was a
bit more subjective. Like they'd debate
it. Uh they'd go back and forth.
Eventually, they would disagree. They'd
commit. They'd move on with their lives.
Everybody on this team, other than Yi
and I, they leave the office at 7:00
p.m.
Yi and I work from 9:00 a.m. to
midnight.
So, after I'm done like doing a good
day's work on my usual kind of stuff, uh
this day I went and I built the
prototype of the RxJava approach. I
found eight representative examples that
I'd seen in past issues and that I just
read in postmortems, and I built
compiling examples for them. Then I did
the same thing for option B. I did the
same thing for option C.
Uh and while I'm doing this, Yi did it
on iOS, I did it on Android. We reviewed
each other's stuff.
And then the next day, everybody comes
in and we show them what we've done and
they say, "Well, yeah, I mean, we
thought option B was better, but like
you guys have done the work. Clearly
option A is better. We can see that.
Thank you." We do something like this
every day.
And at first, our hit rate is not good.
Right? It's like super not good. Uber
would not have paid us to do to spend
this time.
Because we're hunting around, we're
trying to find some kind of unexpected
hidden valuable truth, and most of the
time we're just hitting a knowledge
ceiling we can't get past. And our
intuition for where to hunt is bad.
But, after a few months, we're getting
better at it. Right? A few months later,
we're now the guys who commit the most
code on a team, and instead of
overhearing things
um and then doing it after hours, people
are now going, "Yeah, what should we do?
I don't know. Let's involve Yi and
Atwell." Okay. So, this is like a a few
months into joining this team, we're now
the de facto technical lead.
And we just keep outworking everybody
like basically around us.
Uh a few quarters go by and now we're
like top three committers
uh across the mobile organization at
Uber. And we're also the guys that get
pulled in for a lot of the gnarliest
things across all of mobile
um and also the biggest debates, which
is like a 400-person team.
So, and at this kind of point,
promotions are inevitable. So, they
happen. Okay, I know that like people
listening this may think this is
extreme. Right? This is I also worked
weekends. So, this is like 90, 100 hours
a week, and it hurt. Like physically, my
body hurt and my brain hurt. I had a lot
of headaches at first until I got used
to it. But if you want to be senior
staff at one of the world's best tech
companies by the time you're 25, this is
the only way to do it. To someone who
says like your career growth was luck
and you were lucky to be where you were,
what do you say to that?
Yeah, so luck matters a lot in the
things that happen infrequently.
Right? Like if you do actions every day,
100 times a day,
um and you do those very well, it's not
really luck that those go well for you.
But if you make a decision and you only
make it every 3 years, then luck matters
a lot there. Like selecting which
company you're at. So,
um
yeah, I picked Uber for a reason. Right?
Like I was I was choosy in the company I
picked, but I could have gone wrong.
Um once I was there, you know, there's a
lot of things that I'm doing myself, but
if like I'm not trying to suggest that
everything is solely based off of like
your own merit and that there's always
deterministic mapping between effort and
outcomes. So, you're saying you
increased your chances of luck by
shooting so many shots.
Yeah, well, I guess I'm saying that
um
uh
once you're in the company,
I think like I was going to do well.
Right? I mean, if you outwork everyone
around you and you're fairly smart and
you've got a lot of the right mindsets
um and it's a culture of merit,
then you'll probably do well. But what
if I had joined a company that wasn't
like a merit-based company?
Um and like that would have set me back.
It would have taken me a while to figure
that out.
Um people don't tend to job hop that
well and it doesn't look that good when
you do.
So, joining Uber, yeah, there's a bit of
luck there. And you mentioned you were
choosy in picking Uber. What did you see
at the time that made you pick Uber? And
like what signals are you looking for?
I think that I would spend I would
probably foremost, it's my first
company, spend time sussing out the
quality of the engineers at different
companies. And
um trying to figure out like what is the
process that they use to hire engineers
by cuz that's fairly indicative of the
quality of the engineers that come in.
Processes that hire strong engineers are
um
processes that explicitly test your
brain's ability to reason about
on-the-spot tradeoffs. Um of course,
perform job-relevant skills. Like there
should be like difficult coding aspects.
Um your ability to quickly assimilate
um and discuss information. You there
might be like a hey, here's a five-page
postmortem. Read this thing and then
we're going to debate whether or not
this entire team should be restructured
based on the postmortem. Um and uh you
absolutely should not be able to pass
them unless you have high mental acuity.
Right? Like an an interview that tests
your ability to recall things, your
experience, or just your mindsets does
not build a strong engineering team.
Uh an interview that anyone can pass
regardless of IQ,
uh if they can practice enough, that
does not build a strong engineering
team.
And there's actually a lot of there's
like a commonly large corpus of studies
around how to interview effectively.
The reason that companies don't do it is
it just takes a ton of work to build a
good process.
Um like in a tech org, you have dozens
of different roles and each one needs
different interviews. So, the leadership
team needs to be really dedicated to it.
Like I would say that our interview
process is fairly well designed. I
welcome people to try it out.
But we still are doing like 20
experiments at any given time to try and
improve it.
So then what is it that you would ask
that would actually test for IQ or
something like that?
Yeah, you know what's funny is some some
places will literally do an IQ test up
front and that's not terrible.
Um our our accounting team does that. Um
but if you can come up something that
requires you to hold a lot of concepts
in your head and is also job relevant.
Like you find um an applied programming
task that also involves requires you to
understand a lot of different
requirements at a time and the
requirements are a little bit in
conflict and a little bit harder to
reason about. That kind of thing is
really great.
Um
that postmortem example, right? Like I
read a five-page postmortem
and then just read the whole thing in
like five minutes and then discuss what
are the structural problems with the
team
where one part of the postmortem says
something and another part maybe
conflicts with it three pages down is
the kind of thing that most people and
also chat GPT cannot get anywhere close
to doing.
Interesting. So, it sounds like you're
saying that if someone's IQ is higher,
their job performance will be higher. Uh
yeah, I mean, this is like one of the
most well-researched uh results in
applied psychology. But the reason you
don't notice it as much when you're at
great tech companies is that everybody
that gets in is usually fairly smart
already. There's not a lot of
differentiation between the performance
of people on your team based just on IQ
cuz all of them are already like one or
two standard deviations above the norm.
Um but like that is sure as hell
filtering out people who are you know,
below the median before before they get
in. So then how do you filter among the
people that are already like one to two
standard deviations above? There's a bit
of like how do you design problems that
are they're not just mentally straining.
They're a combination of mentally
straining and experience and like
relevant skills, which shows okay, are
they sharp and have they mastered it and
can they apply it? And some people will
be stronger
when they join. Um there is no interview
process that has an R value of 1.0.
Right? Nothing no interview process in
the world is 100% predictive on the job
performance. Not yet. I maybe maybe
we'll figure it out, Ryan, but
I can tell you that I and no company yet
in the world has it. Well, it's it's
interesting that you say IQ correlates
with on-the-job performance. I'm
actually very seriously considering just
slapping an IQ test in front of some of
my interviews.
>> [laughter]
>> Um because
uh you know, I mean, it's actually a
very honest it's it's part of why
LeetCode is a thing.
Right? Like LeetCode is not that related
to kind of work that you do, but it's
like kind of tricky.
So, it just gets how good people are at
like tricky abstract reasoning. It's
like but it's but the problem is it's so
gameable that you can just practice
LeetCode. IQ test can't practice it. I
don't know. Maybe just slap it up front.
I'm going to try it. I'll I'll probably
try it for PMs first cuz they're harder
to interview generally. Um and also like
my the pass rate for my interview bar
that I've defined for PMs is like super
low.
And I'm just annoyed that I have to keep
interviewing them. So, I mean, I'm going
to slap an IQ test in there and save
some time.
Uh why why are why is interviewing PMs
harder than interviewing software
engineers?
Um so okay, so some aspects of it are
very hard skill oriented. Uh those are
very testable. A lot of the issue is
okay, yes, there's soft skills, but it's
also that this role is generally less
well defined than the engineering role.
It's incredibly well faceted. There also
is not uh such a thing as school for
PMs. Um PMs are different across
different disciplines like software
versus um non-software PMs. The
discipline is younger. So, there just
haven't been as much thought put into
how to interview them very well.
We ended up having to do like a whole
rethink of what is a world-class PM. We
interviewed CEOs of a very variety of
companies to get their take on it
and we like wrote it down and then we
designed a new process that is like
completely different than other
companies do it and I think it's good,
but it just showed like how little I
could borrow from. And look, other
companies have interviews. Like Meta's
PM interview is pretty good. I think it
could be way better. With what? Like
slapping an IQ test?
Well, actually, I mean, it probably
wouldn't hurt.
>> [laughter]
>> If you yeah, if you slapped an IQ test
in front of a PM interview process, it
wouldn't help differentiate between like
excellent and super excellent, but it
would help weed out people very early
and then you could spend more time
differentiating between the good versus
excellent in the rest of your process.
And when I talk to places that do do IQ
tests cuz it's not that uncommon
at places that have very high standards
use something like this, it's always in
the screen stage. It's always just uh
let's filter people out to save them
time and us time. I see. Oh, you're
saying some other companies do run IQ
tests? Yeah, they they do. Yeah. I don't
think there's that many though. I don't
I think this is a little this is uh this
is certainly a move.
I always hear the common take is that it
really doesn't matter how smart you are
past a certain point. It matters more,
you know, how hard you work or your
ability to choose impactful work and you
know, work in a team, etc. What would
you say to that?
IQ is a thing and it it influences how
much you can do all the other things,
but
you definitely need to consciously get
good at other skills. And knowing how to
fiercely prioritize your time super
super important. All right? Like every
time that I do that I'm thinking about
what to work on, I think about three
things.
Which is
uh A, how important is this work? How
what's the expected value of this
initiative over a fixed time window?
B is what uh
what's the probability of its success
with and without me?
And then C is how much time does it take
me? And I multiply A times B, I divide
by C and that's my expected value
creation per hour.
Um and I'm always wanting to maximize
this kind of thing.
What's kind of interesting about this
mindset is that often
you you'll often get into situations
where working on the most important
thing
is not actually we the most valuable
thing you can do with your time.
Because especially early in your career,
early in your career you may find that
by the time that you hear about the
company's top priority, there's a lot of
stuff figured out and it's already super
well staffed. So, joining it'll be fun,
but you may be joining as a cog in a
really well-oiled machine.
Whereas if you go to priority number
three, you find something that's
valuable,
um but in a tougher spot, you can maybe
go in and be a hero. It's interesting
that you say that because um you know,
when I think about prioritization,
obviously it's uh cost-benefit analysis.
Uh you know, benefit divided by cost.
The thing that uh I think is interesting
is that second term where you were
saying that what's the probability of it
succeeding with and without you? Um can
you explain that a little more?
Yeah, I mean this is harder than
I think getting good at estimating
expected value is already a very
difficult thing.
Um and then figuring out like what um
uh uh
how to kind of create uplift is even
harder. But uh at early stages, it will
often be like let's say you're fresh out
of college. At that point, it's fairly
it's often fairly easy. It's just what
is not going to be staffed that's
important.
And then as you get a little bit
further, it's what are the things that
you're uniquely good at?
Um and where does that match with
something that's valuable? And you can
kind of do some fuzzy math, but it's
never going to be three significant
figures of precision. Yeah, I'm I'm kind
of curious about that expected value
calculation as well. Like how
how do you recommend developing that?
What's important to figure out in
determining the benefit? Yeah, um okay,
so there's absolutely things that
everyone can do to get better at this.
Engineers fresh out of college, no
business background, it's not a natural
thing for most of us. So what I
recommend is every time that you have a
director or a PM and they talk about we
really want to move this metric by this
amount for some quarterly goal. Like
maybe it's we want to improve recall on
this model by 10%.
You want to know why they care. Maybe
it's because they want to reduce churn.
They think that'll happen if they
improve recall. And then churn, they're
mapping that in their heads to
additional dollars and cents.
Um if your manager punts on a project,
you kind of want to know what are its
principles befo- behind that. And you
can ask these guys. Like you probably
should use regular time in your
one-on-one to ask why these decisions
are being made. But uh the best possible
case is that you find your company
already has a spreadsheet somewhere with
all the top initiatives or all of the
projects of the quarter and there's a
column that says
here's the expected value or it says
like
here's why we care as a company. If that
column exist, it is gold and you should
read it. Right? You should just every
now and then go read that column. This
is all of the work that other people
have done to calculate expected value or
give some sense of it and you'll pick up
intuition from it.
Talking about management, I'm curious,
what's the story behind you eventually
getting into management? Uh dude, yeah,
I I procrastinated. I put it off
forever.
Um
People at uh my manager at Google told
me I should do it. My manager at Uber
told me I should do it. When I joined
CK, I was told I should do it. And uh we
had really great engineers, you know,
Travis our CEO, he built Uber. Right? He
was the CEO of Uber. So we pulled a lot
of Uber's strongest engineers. They had
friends, they pulled them. It was just
like this really
uh super strong, super tight crew.
And
um
I also had eight engineers that sat
around me and they effectively treated
me like their boss.
And they just uh they asked me what they
should work on and and I came up with
stuff.
So I had all of the fun of being an IC
and of being a
and of having a team and none of the
responsibilities of being a manager. It
was amazing.
Um
and then one day my boss said that I'm
either going to hire a people manager or
you've got to do it.
And he was saying that cuz they did need
a manager. They didn't really have one.
Um
and I thought that when my boss said
this that he was right. They deserved
somebody, but I didn't like the idea of
somebody coming off the streets.
Like of a of a random people manager
managing them.
And I also really didn't like the idea
of somebody coming in and and messing up
my vision for the team, which I thought
was pretty good.
So I was like, all right, I'll do it. Um
I guess.
Uh and I did a terrible job.
Right? Like I uh yeah, I mean I I you
hear about how people how managers will
procrastinate a bit like coding. It's
good for managers to code. But I
procrastinated by so much. I did so much
coding
that there was somebody that joined my
team and after 3 months, he said to me,
"Wait, Brian,
are you my boss?
Like are you my manager? I thought you
were just a really helpful engineer."
Like it was really like how negligent
must I have been in my management
responsibilities for someone to have
said that. It's a real wake-up call. So
after that I stopped procrastinating so
much on these things. I got better at
picking up the management fundamentals.
And then at that point, the portion of
the company that reported to me doubled
roughly every 6 months. Yeah, that's
kind of insane for the part of the
company that reports to you to double
every 6 months. What Why did your team
grow so insanely? Every time an
organization is moved under me from
somebody who's admittedly already pretty
smart, I'd still assume that there's at
least an order of magnitude improvement
that we can make and how this
organization performs.
And I'll just start true seeking with
that team.
Uh I assume that everybody including
myself is wrong just all the time. Um
and I get really, really excited when
somebody says something like, "You know,
Brian, we've been doing this thing for
years and it's like a religious thing.
We believe it so strongly, but I think
it might be wrong." Oh, that gets me
really excited.
And uh I'll give you a small example.
So
um a few years ago, there was uh an
integrations team that was moved under
me.
This team uh they built 1,200 different
integrations with other companies, which
it sounds like a lot because it is.
Uh and their goal was that they want to
basically have all the information about
the entire restaurant industry in one
place. Clearly valuable. Uh each one of
the integrations was originally a very
smart bet. Analysis was done to decide
whether or not it was needed. And it was
built. So now there's a lot of inertia
around maintaining it. Um and the team
works super hard to maintain them and
keep the data quality good. It can be
who manages the team to me says
"Brian,
how important could each of these 1,200
integrations be?" And just [__] great
point, Kendri. That is a lot of
integrations. They can't all be equally
valuable.
So we spent some time digging into that.
We spent a couple days trying to come up
with different formulas to quantify the
value of each of them.
And once we came up with the
distribution, like it's really hard for
anyone to say, "No, you got to keep them
all open." It's just obvious that some
are much less valuable. So we stopped
supporting a bunch of them.
Um the amount of pages that the team
received went down significantly. The
amount of time that the team got back
was very large. And what ended up
happening is that the quality of our
product in aggregate got better. Because
now the integrations that matter are
well supported and we've got time to
build new things. It's just a
win-win-win. So it sounds like when
these teams get moved under you,
you start questioning some of the base
principles. You try to find
the truth in these long-held practices
on the team to uncover these huge wins.
Is that right?
>> That's right. Yeah, 100%.
And often folks often there's a lot of
hints. You kind of want to start with
what are the things that um
the that that people just have
suspicions around. That can be good.
Um that'll get you a few quick wins and
then you'll have to dig a bit deeper.
You mentioned a lot of teams got moved
under you. How does that conversation
usually go? Uh yeah, I mean the
conversation is always really different,
but it's got to be done with empathy.
Um it's a fact of life that if you have
a culture that's based on merit, then in
order for some people to rise to the
top, that other people's ghosts maybe
need to be reduced or some people who
are overall quite capable may still may
need to be managed out. And you can
absolutely have that conversation in an
honest way that says like, "Hey, what we
really need here is this and you haven't
been doing that lately." while still
showing them a lot of appreciation for
what they're they are still doing well
or or for what uh they used to be doing
well. One thing that can happen at some
companies is managers' career growth is
tied to their scope and so they kind of
hold on to it with, you know, everything
that they've got
uh whether or not it's good for the
company or it's a better setup to do so.
And so I'm curious like in those cases
like, you know, why did people give up
their scope or is there not an incentive
structure like that at that company? Uh
yeah, I mean we there shouldn't be an
incentive structure like that. That's
not a good way to set up an incentive
structure in my opinion.
Um
and one of the things that um
the our the head of Picnic and I did a
few years back is rethink how we can
avoid this.
Uh actually it was it was it I think
Travis deserves some credit because
we originally had um a leveling system
and an incentive structure for obvious
reasons very similar to Uber's.
And we knew there were some problems
with it. So Charles and I spent time
improving it.
We presented it to Travis and he read
over it and he's just like dropping
comments everywhere in Google Docs on
how we can each clause can be better.
And he looks up at the end and he he
says, "Guys, like the core problem here
is that this is lazy. You're over
indexing on scope. It's uninsightful.
and you could do so much better. It's
worth your time to do better.
At this point um
I'm so I'm convinced that it could be a
lot better.
And I'm also convinced that a lot of
companies do a bad job. Um
I we ended up spending a ton of time
figuring out more about where other
companies were failing.
Um I think I spent basically every
evening and Saturday for months on this.
Um
Yeah, and
I can get into what we learned, but one
of the big things is really that if you
tie promotions to scope, you're really
over indexing on just one type of
complexity.
And you're also encouraging a lot of
empire building.
When you were going and redesigning the
incentive structure, like what was the
biggest changes you made compared to
what Uber had for this new company?
Okay. Yeah, so if you look at
um what Uber and say meta and Amazon
have, they have a lot of competencies
that read something like um
uh I design processes for the whole
company as a whole.
Um I design I partner with directors on
strategy. I um influence other teams on
undefined goals. Like these are really
position oriented things.
And what this is basically saying is you
get promoted by being loud and being
well positioned.
Uh which kind of [__] up
younger people cuz it's really like be
loud, be good at politics, be good at
maneuvering.
Uh some of that's valuable, but if
everybody does it,
um
people don't actually learn to be able
to good at the corporate other job and
it's bad for the company.
So what we did instead is we started
with these 1,000 different examples of
where people differentiate themselves on
ability. We converted that into 250
human attributes. And then I performed a
principal component analysis to collapse
it down into 12 different where each
dimension is basically like a skill
gradient.
Um and as you climb those skill
gradients your compensation goes up. If
you've got more impact and you're more
skillful on the things that we might
believe matter
then your compensation goes up. Where'd
you source the initial thousand examples
of high performance from?
Yeah, so this is talking to a ton of
engineers.
Um
Uh there's like 12 books that I read. I
also looked through years of our
calibration notes. Every time we do
quarterly calibration, we'll talk about
um why this engineer did well. So I just
scraped all of that out. Um and then
wrote them all down. It's about a
thousand. Um
and uh I made certain that they're all
things that I knew personally had
actually happened. They weren't
[__]
Um
Otherwise, you could again get into a
situation where
um
it the skill gradient is [__] at the
high levels, right? It's like just an
unachievable dream.
What are the biggest attributes that
differ from well-known ladders? Cuz
everyone who works at these big tech
companies kind of knows the the
existing. So what are the things that
you introduced that are different
because of this analysis?
Yeah, I think the the probably main
difference is this
is this emphasize on on truth seeking
and like how you perform very well
instead of what you perform very well.
Right? If you look at I think meta's
level leveling guide, it'll say you have
to be able to like influence other teams
at E6 with good ideas. And in our
ladder, we'll say something like you
have to be right most of the time when
questioning a foundational engineering
and product decision or industry norm.
It's not so much about convincing
people. It's how good are you at
actually getting good ideas?
Um and there's a separate competency on
how good you are at communicating ideas,
which we define what good looks like.
Um
Uh instead of just saying it's about
like the social kind of social proof
thing. I see. But then how do you
determine if it's good communication or
not? You give a lot of examples, right?
In your in your your document where you
define these things, you say, "Okay,
here's the verbal description of what it
means. And here's a few examples." And
then when uh engineers are scoring
themselves, they can kind of look at the
examples and go, "Well,
I mean, if I'm being honest, was I that
good?"
Right? If I look at this artifact, does
it stand up to that? I'm not sure how it
fixes the the politics
social problem of calibrating engineers
because you could have a manager that
lists out those examples, but says them
in a biased way. So like how do you get
rid of that incentivizing politics?
Okay. Yeah, so this is um
still a thing that managers could try to
do. It's a little bit uh
um
the kinds of things that they would
posture around would be different
though, right? Like the
um
engineers aren't going to spend as much
time trying to figure out how do I
how do I like
design company-wide processes say or
like explicitly influencing other teams
is not necessarily the goal anymore.
So uh you might have people posturing
around being good at communication
um
and exaggerating that, but at least
they're trying to get good at
communication or they're trying to get
good at truth seeking, which is almost
always beneficial as opposed to
something that's not always beneficial.
Um
There are still though things you can do
to protect against this and the answer
is it's like a lot of work. Right? You
have to
um like spot check managers.
Um and if you find them exaggerating it,
you have to fire them.
Easier said than done. I'm curious like
how
>> Is it? Well, I mean, I don't know. Who
wants a liar on their team?
There was someone else that I had on
before and he said that's a big problem
in management is it's someone who is bad
for some reason
but is well-liked. They're one of the
biggest problems because it's difficult
to fire them.
Uh what would you say to that?
Yeah, I You know, it's funny cuz I I do
hear this, but I don't think that it's
really true. Right? Like it feels very
difficult to fire them if you're a
front-line manager cuz you like them and
you see kind of the social bonds. But
often there's a bit of similar and
resentment about that person. The people
on the on the team who are working hard,
they're like, "Yeah, man, Joe's so
great, but why the [__] did he just go
home at 2:00 p.m.?
Like why am I working at 6:00 p.m.? I
feel like a chump." Right? So if you
remove this person, immediately it may
feel bad, but a month later the whole
team will be happier. You've mentioned
truth seeking a lot in this this new
ladder and I'm kind of curious like how
do you prove truth seeking? Like how do
you give examples of someone that that
did that well?
Yeah, I mean, a lot of it is um have you
uncovered something that
um
that is is like highly unconventional?
Um
Um and there's a a bunch of different
dimensions that could result in that.
Like oh, it was actually in plain sight
for a while and nobody found it even
though it's highly valuable. It's sort
of a signal.
Or is it different than what every other
company does, but for because our
constraints are different,
um it
uh
it's actually it's beneficial to go
against the grain. Like just some
there's a a bunch of different
dimensions that result in truth seeking
being being difficult that you can latch
onto.
Um
Uh
And then there is a bit of subjectivity.
You know, there's not like uh you could
you have to kind of write it down and
then calibrate managers on how to score
these things.
Um it's not as easy as counting PR stats
is, but we all know that that's not a
great way to judge engineers. Yeah,
yeah.
Well, a lot of companies have some sort
of measure of like directional
contribution. Like you know, how did
they how did you change the direction of
everyone based on your contributions?
And that sounds very similar to truth
seeking here.
Yeah, I mean, it's it's not like these
are um
the way the tech companies have designed
their their leveling frameworks, their
incentive structures are not completely
broken. And in many ways, they're just
way better than what exists in the like
Dilbert-esque era of the 1980s. Um
there's some ways
they've they've been actually I think
kind of nicely designed to reward you
once you get into a specific position.
Um and they're very good at rewarding
you once outcomes are achieved.
Um they're a little bit less about the
leading indicators.
Um but you're not going to get wildly
different results. You'll just make it a
little harder for some people and a
little easier for some other people. Uh
yeah, one thing I'm curious about cuz
like a lot of tech companies, they they
incentivize the result, not necessarily
the thing before that happens before the
result. And so yeah, is there a case
where you could have an engineer does a
phenomenal job on something that gets
deprioritized and they would still get
rewarded? Oh yeah, of course. Yeah.
Okay. Yeah, maybe if you're like at the
highest level, you should have the
business savvy to know that it's not
going to be, but if you're if you do
phenomenal work toward the project and
for no reason related to you, this thing
gets canceled, you've still done
phenomenal work and we can still measure
that you've been doing phenomenal work
and reward you for that. It's kind of
our fault as our fault as leaders that
it got canceled so late.
One thing I'm curious about is and I
think companies like Amazon are famous
for, you know, not really rewarding the
high performers that much. And I was
curious to ask you because you've worked
on company design for a while now or
engineering organization design is like
why do these companies not reward their
highest performers?
I held off saying this, but a lot of it
is just cuz they can get away with it.
Right? Like they think, "Oh, the equity
went up by a lot.
Um maybe it's a little bit unjust to pay
you less because your equity went up. I
think it's unjust. That's basically your
investment. You have got a good
investment result. It shouldn't factor
in the future decisions. But, they can
get away with doing it because people
are mostly happy they got a lot of
appreciation. We actually made a point
of not doing that earlier on.
I just think it's if you design your
company processes around being just,
it's going to be better for you in the
long run, but you kind of just got to
believe that. You know, we've been
talking a lot about big tech and I know
you started off
at Google and I'm kind of curious like,
you know, what what was that like or
what did you get from starting at
Google?
I think the main thing that I got from
working at Google is I got
a real deep-seated skepticism for how
well tech companies are run.
Um, in my all right, so I joined Google
and in my first week I see there's a guy
on my team doesn't do any work.
And let's call him Frank.
I talked to my manager about it. I'm
like, what's the deal with Frank, yo?
That's not how I talked, but you get the
point. Um, and my boss says
Yeah, I know, but he's such a nice guy,
Brian. So, just lay off. I talked to my
engineering director shortly after this
and I say the same thing. He
is a little bit embarrassed. Like he
knows that there's something off about
having people that don't do work, but he
repeats the same thing, which is that
Brian, this guy's a really great guy and
everybody likes him.
Um
I actually complained a lot about it and
I can't prove anything, but he was
eventually moved off my team onto a team
where no one would complain because no
one on the team did any work.
Um, the team was just like they were
building demos for the gift shop or
something like that. So, what you got
from that is that
um, like that's that's a Google problem.
And that he should have been fired.
Yeah, absolutely. Or or, yeah, he should
have been fired or there should have
been a serious conversation.
Right? And be like, so, you've been here
for a while, you've done good work.
We're still paying you. Like, could you
could you do work again?
Right? You can't expect us to keep
paying you if you don't and then he
might have gotten back into it. Why do
you think that that hard conversation
wasn't had at Google?
I mean, so there is something Google
specific that exists there, which I can
get back to, but generally at large
companies the performance of the company
is fairly decoupled from the performance
of individual teams. So, it does become
easier for this kind of thing to to
happen for
managers to do things that are
convenient for themselves even if it
hurts the company.
But, there's also this natural thing
that happens at companies of any size
where it takes a lot of energy to raise
a standard.
And it takes very little energy to lower
it. Few people will complain if you
suddenly ask everyone to do less work.
Which means if you have entropy in a
system, standards will naturally fall
over time
until the company dies. It'll just keep
going down until the company dies or
until some kind of trauma kicks it back
into place. Right? Like, if you're a if
you're at Google right now, the DeepMind
team, oh, they're working hard.
Right? Like Google's like Alphabet's
like, oh, there's an existential threat
to our existence. The DeepMind team
better work hard now. I mean, entropy
will always lower the bar and there was
this thing at Google which I cannot
prove existed, but several managers at
Google told me it. So, I haven't seen it
in writing, but like a VP and some
managers told me it existed that around
a decade ago Google had this policy
where they wanted to keep as many smart
people on staff as possible
um, even if they weren't working anymore
cuz maybe they'd work hard again in the
future and they didn't want their
competitors to have them. So, that's
just a super unique Google thing. I
mean, that's kind of crazy. I don't know
of any other company that's done that. I
see. And do you think there's any merit
in that kind of hiring strategy? No,
because there's a lot of smart people in
the world. I think it's fairly difficult
to have a monopoly on intelligence.
And now at this point I'm kind of
curious like, what are you working on
these days and maybe we can talk about
that a little.
Yeah, okay. So,
um
it's fairly secret and we don't usually
talk about it with reporters cuz we're
in stealth. But, I talked to Travis
about it and he said I could give you a
bit more than I've given to anybody
before. So, I'll give you some stuff.
I'll give you the whole like thesis of
the company. The core insight is that no
one should cook their own food in a few
dec- in
no one should cook their own food.
And
we know that people don't want to
because when you look at places with
lower costs of labor,
like middle upper class people, they
don't cook anymore. Like of course they
don't. They save they choose to save 10
hours of their time a week and take it
back.
Um
and
if you
um
uh, if you look at the US
there's like Uber Eats, there's
DoorDash. These things are fairly
convenient.
They offer some of that super expensive,
so nobody can use them every day.
Um, if
you know, if these things were way
cheaper though, that would work. And
here's the second core insight which is
that there's a ton of avoidable waste in
the food supply chain.
Um, so we're just kind of scratching the
surface on this, but we've built we've
built robots that
um, reduce labor costs in real
restaurants by 50%.
Um, we've built this like lunch
logistics network that
uh, reduces the cost of a meal overall
30-40%.
We have
um
what else? We've got this real estate
thing where the cost per meal is half of
what normal cost per meals are and we
also have the software product called
Otter processes 18% of the world's
orders and makes them a bit more
efficient. And we've we've got all these
things going going. Some of them are
early, some of them have a lot of
customers, but it shows just how much of
inefficiency can be squeezed out.
It shows that if you're willing to spend
the R&D money, you can make real moves
at lowering the cost of a food that's
made just for you, like fresh,
um, without any labor on your part.
Uh
so
if the size of the pie is big enough, we
can make this happen and
American spend $2.5 trillion a year on
food.
So, if you if you think about like the
most conservative cost modeling possible
like you just imagine that you redesign
this whole like supply chain, uh, you
have super thin margins. This is $5
trillion sitting on a table right now
just waiting for the companies that go
and solve this problem.
And
that will happen eventually no matter
what. Right? Eventually robots are going
to do all of it.
But, we think that we can do a lot of
work now to to enable this and then
hopefully we capture a few trillion
dollars of value and our partners
capture a few trillion as well. You
know, one of the things that I'm most
curious about cuz I remember at some
point I was living in SF and I got an
invite to a recruiting event for Cloud
Kitchens. I never heard about it. It
said, you know, we're a large stealth
startup. Hey, we're going to treat you
to dinner. Just come and listen about
it. And it was something I never heard
about, but it had Travis's name.
One of the most unusual hiring
strategies I've seen for a company that
scale. So, I'm curious, why is this
company so strict on privacy?
Yeah, right. So, I mean, we are super
strict. You're right. And we don't have
a corporate website.
Um, we ask employees not to post that
they work here on LinkedIn. We were
doing a fairly good compliance around
um, we don't have any PR people. Here's
why we wouldn't have done it. And I'll
tell you why we did it. When you're
founding a company, if you're if you're
very public in the media, it's easier to
raise money. It's
um, easier to hire.
It's also makes the founder's ego swell.
All these great stuff.
And um, we uh, our CEO built Uber. He's
a billionaire. He's got a good network.
He's got funding and his ego is doing
just fine. So, these upsides didn't
really mean a lot to us.
But, the downsides of being public did.
If you look at 2018
um, and you look at like headlines,
sentiment, uh, you can actually go and
check this. I've checked it. Um
it took this nose dive towards the
negativity after Cambridge Analytica
happened. The US populace just loved
reading shitty news about tech
companies. So, if you're working for a
tech company at that time, you're
constantly reading bad things about
yourself.
And it's very distracting to employees
and especially distracting to
leadership. It takes your mind off of
innovation and puts you more into a
damage control place.
Um, and then the other thing is that we
really wanted to minimize the amount of
competitors we had.
If you've got a good idea and your
founding team has a strong track record
and you're visible
other people will see that who are
enterprising go, maybe I'll just do
that. Right? Like when we launched in
Korea, we were very public about it. We
talked reporters. There wasn't just one
competitor or two or there was three.
There was a whole ecosystem of people
that decided to compete with us just
because we had a famous starting team.
Uh, and then the same thing happened in
the US where this company received $150
million. They got a Vision Fund
investment even though they had very
little going on for them.
And yeah, they were never going to make
it. Right? They never had a hope.
But, it was still annoying.
It was still distracting for us. And the
answer is just shut up and be quiet. And
like build great stuff
and don't talk about it and then win
silently and confidently.
I mean, this to me is like the very
opposite. I see a lot of other companies
they they get started and they start
with distribution actually. Like they
have these these rage bait products that
go out and explode on Twitter and then,
you know, you people start using it from
that. And there's obvious benefits to
that. it's like you get users, you get
people talking about it and all the
other benefits that come with that. Um
so like how are you handling
distribution then if you're so quiet? A
lot of the stuff that we do is B2B.
Um and you can still do marketing around
individual products. We have products
that we talk about quite a bit, right?
We have Picnic, there's Otter, hundreds
of thousands of restaurants use it and
there's ads around those things. We just
don't talk about our core company as
much.
Uh so the main thing that it it adds a
bit of difficulty around is is hiring.
So like people like me have to go on
famous podcasts, you know, and see if
they can mitigate that a bit.
>> [laughter]
>> Right? Um but uh
I think it's it's not as hard for a
sales as you'd expect. Coming to the end
of the conversation, uh I just want to
go over some career reflections. And so
one thing that I'm always curious about
is when you think back over your career,
what's your biggest career regret?
So I've messed up a lot of things,
especially early stage. And there's
things that you know, you'd think I
might regret and that I don't. All
right, so I was a first-year undergrad,
I was interning at Apple.
And I was building this like tweak to
the OS, this uh a fork of it that it
made the phone easier to use in
sunlight, which is a problem at the
time.
And I remember I was showing it to my
mentor at lunch and it just so happened
that Steve was sitting right next the
table beside me. So I mentor, Ken,
amazing guy,
just starts like really spouting off on
how good this prototype is. He's She's
like super loud. He's like
"This is a game changer for the company.
It's going to differentiate us so much.
It's going to make us so much money."
He's like super loud. And Steve hears
and he's like "All right, let me check
out this thing."
He walks over, he sits right in front of
me.
And
um Ken's still going.
And I'm like Ken Ken Ken, wait, come on,
it's not that big a deal. It's like 50
100 lines of code. It wasn't even that
hard.
Uh
>> [sighs]
>> Steve like sighs. You know, you could
see his why did I sit down. He rolls his
eyes and then Ken's trying to win him
back, but Steve just like walks away.
Right? He doesn't say anything.
And at this point Ken explains to me
that uh just how badly I [__] up.
Right? Not only did you lose your chance
to impress this industry icon, which is
like would be a story for your life, but
also
it's very likely that this thing that
you've been working on will now never
see the light of day because my team
does not have funding for it. This is
just a thing you're trying out, Brian.
So you've by doing this, you've killed
it.
Um and
you know, the the thing here is that I
didn't know anything about products, how
to pitch it, and I was a really awkward
18 19-year-old kid.
So there was really very little chance
that that was ever going to go right.
And even that night when I got home, I
didn't feel too bad. I was just like
"Oh, I now know I'm an awkward kid and I
should learn how to pitch better, I
guess." Right? Um yeah, that kind of
thing I don't regret cuz I couldn't have
done better.
What I do regret is the places where
I like knew what I should do.
Um where
um maybe I was just too uncomfortable
communicating about it or I was worried
I'd do a bad job, so I didn't bother.
Those are the kind of things I'm
embarrassed about.
And do you have a concrete example? I
don't know if I have a concrete example
that I can say without making people
feel bad.
But but it's like imagine you're making
a decision and
um
uh and you're you're halfway through it,
you realize it's the wrong thing
and you just kind of go with it. Maybe
you're just 2 years in your career.
That's a really easy thing to do, but
you should be really honest like
actually guys, we I was way off and now
we're our product's off track. We can
keep going forwards, but everyone on
this team deserves to know that I made a
mistake in case we want to go and
correct it. Um like even not knowing
whether or not we would have corrected
it, I still look back on that and I'm
like that wasn't great. I should have
been more honest. So the regret is I
guess not seeking towards the truth.
Like if you knew there was a problem in
the middle of an initiative to like cut
it or at least share that we might want
to reconsider.
Yeah, that's right. And I think you you
kind of I feel like you have owe
even if you think you can't convince
people, you owe them a bit of the
benefit of the doubt that they're going
to be receptive, they're going to hear
you out. Um and it's you you kind of
have to try. If they ignore you, it's
fine. If if you're wrong, it's also very
fine.
Um but you should try and you should get
better at being able to communicate that
kind of thing.
You mentioned Travis earlier. I'm
curious, do you have any interesting
stories working directly with Travis?
Yeah, I don't know. I mean I've got a
lot, but uh so okay, here's what
everybody knows about Travis Kalanick,
uh intense polymath.
What people don't know is like intense
dad energy, right? Uh we had this
offsite where was the senior engineering
leaders and Travis. It's over the
weekend and we've got, you know, like
work sessions. In between them, Travis
is just like having a blast teaching
people how to play backgammon. And he's
also
almost perfect like a world-class water
skier. So he's coaching people how to
water ski.
And he's super patient with us, even
those of us that are like pretty
unathletic,
which let's be honest, we're engineers,
so it's like most of us. He's pretty
patient with with like all of us.
>> [laughter]
>> And I needed a lot of help.
It sounds like you went to Cloud
Kitchens from Uber in large part because
Travis Kalanick was founding it and I'm
curious about picking companies based on
the founder. And so in your case, like
when you reflect on that, like was that
a good decision? Would you recommend
that for others?
Yeah, I think it can make a lot of sense
for founder-led early-stage companies.
Cuz these companies a lot of what
matters is what is their composition
and what is their culture. And and
that's
and like what are their standards and
a lot of the two points there, they're
just being set from the top at a company
where you have somebody with that much
control.
And so if you got a really good person,
it can be just a huge multiplier for the
effectiveness of the company. Well, a
lot of others.
Um
and it also can also go very much the
other way if you don't have the right
person in charge.
You mentioned uh receiving advice from
other people and I'm curious, is there a
single advice that impacted your career
most?
Okay, is this is gold. I've got
something. I had this computer science
teacher in high school and I would ask
them a lot of questions and every time I
asked a question, their answer would be
like "Brian, figure it out for
yourself."
And and like I actually never
I never learned whether or not it was
because this was a good pedagogy or if
they just didn't know the answer. Right?
It's possible they knew nothing about
computer science. But uh it didn't
really matter. It's very good advice
because 95% of everything that you learn
professionally it is going to be
self-directed learning. So you just got
to get comfortable with that and accept
that you always have to be learning
um
and like pushing yourself to to to go
kind of beyond your the immediate area
at which you're you're comfortable. Was
there a top book that impacted your
career?
Um
no. So instead I'll give you kind of a
cheesy answer for books that I'd
recommend. Um
if you are like a front engineer, I'd
recommend you read how to pass the
system design interview.
And if you're like an MLE or back end,
read something like how to pass the PM
interview.
What these books will do is they're
designed to help you cheese your way
through an interview process, which is
fine.
But what's cool about them is that they
are designed to give you a very broad
and superficial understanding of a
domain that you're not already very
familiar with.
And uh if you go and you do the
exercises, you'll actually remember it.
So it'll stick in your head and then you
will have a good ability to have
productive conversations with people
that are in other roles than you. And
that's very valuable. It'll also give
you some foundation to learn stuff in
that domain.
If you could go back to yourself when
you just entered the industry and give
advice to yourself, what would you say?
Uh I'd probably say younger self,
uh be be more courageous and less
embarrassed. You're going to have fail a
lot and it's fine.
That's easier said than done. Like
I feel like embarrassment is like you
just feel it.
Yeah, I know. I mean but uh
this would be the opening two sentences
before a larger conversation
about how to search your own feelings
and understand them.
Uh
you know, maybe it would actually be
Brian, you should go to therapy. That
that might also be good advice. I think
it's it's generally helpful to uh to be
more in touch with your own emotions for
your own sake and it helps you relate
with other people better.
Cool. All right, well, yeah, thank you
so much for your time today. Really
appreciate it, Brian. Yeah, it's fun,
Brian.
Thanks for listening to the podcast. I
don't sell anything or do sponsorships,
but if you want to help out with the
podcast, you can support by engaging
with the content on YouTube or on
Spotify. If you want to drop a review,
that'll be super helpful. And if there's
any guests that you want to bring on,
too, please let me know. I feel like
sourcing very senior ICs, there's no
well-studied list out there on Google
that I can just search this up. So if
there's someone in your org or at your
company who you really look up to and
you want to hear their career story, let
me know and I'll reach out to them.